Guide to the Technology and Society Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Technology and Society Collection
1946-1962
RU 472
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
49.25
(108 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, research data, interviews, statistics, reports, and printed material compiled to document studies made in twelve American companies by the Yale Technology Project and related material.
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 33-D (YRG 33-D), Records of the Yale Technology and Society Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, research data, interviews, statistics, reports, and printed material compiled to document studies made in twelve American companies by the Yale Technology Project and related material. Included are profiles of communities in economic crisis, analyses of technology and industrial organizations, and statistical data on worker attitudes and industrial relations problems. There are approximately 2000 interviews with workers, covering the subjects' lives, history, work experiences, values, and emotions. The research led to the publication of well-known works such as "Man on the Assembly Line," and "Toward the Automatic Factory". Many of the studies were never formally published.
The twelve studies varied widely in duration, size, research topics and methodology. Many of the studies were consulting programs (conducted by Charles R. Walker Associates) as well as research projects (conducted by the Yale Technology Project). In the consulting programs, such as the one at Avco, the consultants became involved with the management process, sometimes even acting as managers, but there is no substantial difference in the kinds of material contained in the files of these different kinds of studies. All of the studies were directed by Charles R. Walker, the Director of the Yale Technology Project. Frederick Richardson was the co-researcher for the IBM and Ford studies. Robert H. Guest, Arthur Turner and Frank J. Jasinski joined Walker later and formed a research and consulting team.
All of the studies have been arranged in a similar manner. An introduction and an outline for each study are included in the Guide to the Collection. File 1 of each study contains copies of the introduction and outline and tables of contents for the files of particular importance or complexity. The tables of contents briefly describe all the items in the files covered. Copies of the tables are also placed in the appropriate files. Every item in every file has been labeled with its file number,
The material has been filed in the following general order:
Background (guide, correspondence, methodology, preliminary notes)
Data (interviews, observations, statistics and diagrams)
Reports (notes, drafts and final reports)
Duplicate Material
Each file has two labels indicating its general category and specific contents.
The Guide to the Collection provides an overview of all the studies, indicating the nature of each study and the general contents of the files. After a particular study has been selected, the introductory materials and the tables of contents in file 1 should be reviewed. Often the best introduction to the purposes, data and conclusions of a study is found in a comprehensive final report. Organizational charts are usually important and should be studied. Unless this preparatory material is understood, the raw data - interviews, observations, statistics or diagrams - is likely to be baffling and might well be misinterpreted.
In all of the published books and articles derived from the studies, the names or other identifying characteristics (such as exact location) of the companies were never revealed. Confidentiality was usually promised at the beginning of research, and that promise is presumably still in effect.
The library accompanying the files contains books on economic and social affairs donated by Mr. Walker and many books specifically purchased for the Collection. Of special importance are the books derived from the Yale Technology Project studies. These books have been placed in a separate group.
Arrangement
The records are arranged as follows: I. General Guide. II. Yale Technology and Society Project Pamphlets. III. General Motors Study. IV. Raytheon Study. V. Ford Study. VI. Kodak Study. VII. Dresser Study. VIII. U.S. Steel Study. IX. IBM Study. X. General Electric Study. XI. Merck Study. XII. Jones and Laughlin Steel Study. XIII. New York Trust Study. XIV. AVCO Study. XV. Research Files. XVI. Research Pamphlets. XVII. Research Periodicals and Government Publications.
Appendix: Annotated List of the Studies
Ford. Rouge Plant, Michigan, 1946. A brief study of corporate policy and the assembly line. Major data: management interviews, observations, statistics on labor problems. (18 files)
IBM. Endicott, New York, 1946-1947. Study of improved morale through simplifying the organization and job enlargement, despite rapid growth. Major data: Management interviews, diagrams of organization and work-flow. (79 files)
US Steel. Ellwood City, Pennsylvania and Lorain, Ohio. 1946-1956. Ellwood City: study of the planned departure of the steel mill and its effect on the community. Lorain: study of automation. Major data: interviews with management, workers, union officials, community members. (222 files)
Dresser. Bradford, Pennsylvania and Connersville, Indiana. 1949-50. Consulting project on morale within the plants and their their relations with the corporation. Major data: management, worker and union interviews, and observations. (23 files)
Kodak. Rochester, New York, 1949-1951. Consulting report on program of management-worker meetings. Major data: management and worker interviews. (9 files)
GM. Framingham, Massachusetts, Linden, New Jersey, Meriden, Connecticut, 1949-1957. Framingham: study of workers and foremen on the assembly line. Linden: study of workers and of improvements in management. Meriden: study of technical change at a New Departure plant. Major data: management, worker and union interviews; observation of foremen. (419 files)
Jones and Laughlin. Pittsburgh and Aliquippa, Pennsylvania; Cleveland, Ohio. Pittsburgh Works: labor relations and training. Monongahela Railroad, Pittsburgh: labor relations and human relations. Alquippa: labor relations. Otis Works, Cleveland: labor relations and management. Major data: management interviews and observations. (51 files) 1950-1953.
Merck. Rahway New Jersey, 1951-1952. Consulting study of supervisory and worker morale. Major data: management and worker interviews. (54 files)
New York Trust. New York City, 1953-1954. Consulting study of management training and morale. Major data: management interviews. (44 files)
Avco. Stratford, Connecticut, 1953-1957. Consulting study on management morale. Major data: management interviews, notes on meetings, foreman observation. (72 files)
GE. Schenectady and Syracuse, New York, 1957-1959. Study of management organization and product development operation. Major data: management and worker interviews. (83 files)
Raytheon. Massachusetts and Maine, 1958-1962. Research on work and morale, plus consulting on management problems. Major data: management and worker interviews, job enlargement experiment. (173 files)
Technological innovations; Technology -- Social aspects; Technology assessment; Working class; Industrial relations; Industrial sociology; Walker, Charles R. (Charles Rumford), 1893-1974; Guest, Robert H., 1916-; Turner, Arthur N. (Arthur Nicholson), 1921-; Udy, Stanley H., 1928-; Yale Technology Project; United States Steel Corporation; General Motors Corporation; International Business Machines Corporation; Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation; Merck & Co; New York Trust Company; Avco Corporation; General Electric Company; Raytheon Company; Ford Motor Company; Eastman Kodak Company; Dresser Industries, inc
- Yale Technology Project records, Accession 1985-A-066
  - General guide, Series I
    - General Files
      - Yale Technology Project Files (Box 2, Box 1, Folder 1-23)
      - Personal Papers and Correspondence of YTP Staff (Box 3, Box 2, Folder 24-44)
      - Consulting Papers (Box 3, Folder 45-54)
      - Speeches (Box 4, Box 3, Folder 55-62)
      - Books, Articles and Essays by YTP Staff (Box 5, Box 4, Folder 63-103)
      - Professional Papers (Box 5, Folder 104-121)
      - Bibliography (Box 6, Folder 122-124)
      - Clippings (Box 6, Folder 125-128)
  - Yale Technology and Society Project pamphlets, Series II
    - Pamphlets (Box 7, Folder 1-32)
  - General Motors Study, Series III
    Scope and Contents
    The study of General Motors spanned ten years and included five distinct though overlapping studies at two plants (Framingham, Massachusetts and Linden New Jersey) and one at a ballbearing plant in Connecticut (New Departure in Meriden). Both Framingham hourly workers and Linden hourly workers were studied intensively. Framingham foremen were interviewed and observed in minute detail, while Linden foremen were studied as part of the Workers study and Crisis study. At GM Detroit's request, the researchers conducted a survey of Linden in crisis (1953) and then three years later a follow-up study of Linden's great improvement under a new Plant Manager. A small investigation of the New Departure Plant at Meriden was made as part of an inquiry into "Technology and Organization" in conjunction with the survey of a General Electric facility. The New Departure investigation is separate from the auto assembly line studies at Framingham and Linden.
    Framingham workers
    In June, 1949, the Yale researchers began study of a new plant with a youthful workforce in Framingham, Mass. These men were fairly well-educated, 3 out of 4 were married and about the same number were WWII Veterans. One-hundred and eighty workers were interviewed extensively in their homes.
    Factual data was taken from personnel records, from the questioning of the workers regarding his work group, interaction, type of jobs worked on at Framingham, union meetings attended and from his description of jobs held prior to his Framingham job (the workers had undergone a significant change in work experience from the old job to the new one). Questions were asked to draw out the worker's attitudes and opinions. These questions were often open-ended because they may have evoked a strong emotional response. A two-column scale rating the Likes and Dislikes of the workers was developed. Also, a sketch of the "geography" of the man's job: work flow, spatial relationship in the work environment and social interaction pattern. The interview was designed to bring out the attitudes and opinions the worker had about his job, his relationship to management and other workers, the working conditions, pay and promotions and his relation to the union.
    Results: the majority of the workers disliked the mechanical pacing and repetitive character of their jobs. Interest in work varied directly with the number of operations performed (most workers performed only one or two operations every minute). Inability to "get quality" irritated a large number of workers. Pay and security were the most important "likes" with the immediate job as the number one "dislike."
    There was little possible social interaction. Noise, pace and the character of the work frustrated the men. The nature of the assembly line process precluded functional interdependence. The few who did sub-assembly work in a group were favorably aware of their "team." The few who could move into different operations within their section recognized the variety and mobility as favorable characteristics.
    Pay was a major incentive for taking a job at Framingham. Steady and secure employment motivated many men to stay.
    There was a "healthy" two-way interaction between the foreman and the worker, but little interaction between the worker and higher levels of supervision. The workers generally had a high opinion of their foremen, but did not consider it to be of prime importance in deciding whether or not they liked their jobs.
    There was little job mobility. Workers generally desired to be transferred to non straight production jobs as the following: foreman, utilityman, repairman, maintenance, inspection or clerical worker, etc.
    A correlation was found to exist between absenteeism and turnover and mass production characteristics.
    Two-thirds of the sample were favorable to the Union. Half of the workers felt that the company did not do much of anything for the men.
    Linden workers
    One major question was left unanswered by the Framingham - study: how well could workers adjust in time to assembly line work?
    Linden was chosen as a research site to help answer this question. It was an old integrated plant and the interviews were confined to workers with at least 12 years of seniority.
    Two-hundred and two workers were interviewed in their homes. The interviews, though more detailed and non-directive than the Framingham interviews, covered the same material. In general the Linden workers study confirmed the findings of the Framingham investigation. The workers were not better adjusted and actually disliked their jobs more intensely than the Framingham workers. Additionally, several non-production men and 18 workers who had quit were interviewed, only to underline the sources of dissatisfaction in the mass-production work.
    The Linden Crisis Study
    The Framingham and Linden studies raised the question of the importance of supervision. This question was underlined by the crisis situation at Linden. GM Detroit Management requested a study be done of all levels of production management. The researchers found a good deal of pressure for high production, but also found some individuals who were able to handle it. There were, it seemed, certain qualities needed by a foreman during times of crisis. Overtime had an expensive and negative effect on supervisory morale which nullified sporadic production increases.
    The Framingham Foremen Study
    The foreman, it appeared, was in a particularly important position in terms of communicating management's policies to the worker. Fifty-five of the foremen at Framingham were interviewed. They were found to act as "buffers" between management and the worker: to counteract pressure and impersonality caused by the assembly line.
    During the summer of 1954 all 55 foremen were observed for an eight-hour day. The observer spent 3 hours in the department the day before in order to familiarize himself with the foreman's job. Each observation was 40 to 70 pages in typed length. There were 32,652 incidents in total for all of the foremen. The researchers found that the pattern of a foreman's time distribution was both a reflection of his ability, training or experience, and the result of conditions beyond his control. Even the best foremen when faced with the problems of absenteeism, mechanical difficulties, changes in schedule or material shortages, had to devote an inordinate amount of time to these problems instead of perfoming his primary and supervisory duties.
    The Linden Follow-Up Study, 1956-1957
    Since 1953 a new plant manager had succeeded in greatly improving performance records (and human relations) at Linden. This study documents changes that were made and the reactions of all levels of organization. Top and middle management, supervisors and foremen, workers and others were interviewed.
    New Departure, 1956-1957
    A ball-bearing factory (at Meriden, Connecticut) in GM's New Departure Division was experiencing difficulties in introducing a new manufacturing system - a problem in technological change. After deciding that the organization (or social system) of the factory was an important factor in the problem, the plant management promoted changes in the old rigid vertical hierarchy. A task-oriented system was developed which brought together all those involved in the technological change, thus forming horizontal and diagonal working relationships that crossed the old hierarchical boundaries. A major element of the new system was a series of planning meetings attended by all levels of management and some hourly workers. The research study included interviews with management officials and an intensive analysis of the technology.
    General material on the studies is contained in the final reports, in the background files in each study, and in the correspondence and conferences with GM management concerning the research projects. The final reports for each study usually include a statement of the purpose and methods of the study as well as the presentation of the information gathered and the conclusions and recommendations of the researchers.
    Each distinct study has been arranged and filed separately, with two exceptions. A considerable amount of material concerns all of the studies in general, and this has been collected under General GM (I.). In addition, reports that were derived from both the Linden and the Framingham studies (rather than from one alone) are in a separate section (V.).
    The files for each study follow a general pattern: background, company documents, data (mainly interviews and observations), notes and analysis, drafts and final reports. The drafts are not likely to provide any significant data beyond what is in the final reports. While the GM company documents (I., C., 017-043) contain much that is of little importance, they also include some material that is quite valuable.
    Files that are complex or particularly important have tables of contents, with one copy placed in the file and one copy accompanying this guide. Every item in every file is numbered f ____ i _____. If any item is lost, a copy may be available in the duplicate files. Copies of the books written about GM are not placed within the files themselves but are kept with the Technology and Society Collection.
    - General Motors study
      - Background (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
      - Discussions and Correspondence with GM (Box 8, Folder 6-16)
      - Company Documents (Box 11, Box 8, Folder 17-43, Box 10, Box 9)
      - Framingham, MA Workers
        - Background (Box 11, Folder 44-50)
        - Preliminary Worker Interviews (Box 11, Folder 51-54)
        - Worker Interviews (Box 11, Folder 55-95, Box 13, Box 12, Box 14)
        - Interview Analysis (Box 14, Folder 96-111, Box 15)
        - Reports (Box 15, Folder 112-129, Box 16)
      - Framingham Foremen
        - Interview Background (Box 16, Folder 130-136, Box 17)
        - Management and Union interviews (Box 17, Folder 137-140)
        - Foremen Interviews (Box 17, Folder 141-146)
        - Interview Analysis (Box 17, Folder 147-149)
        - Forement Observation Background (Box 17, Folder 150-153)
        - Forement Observations (Box 19, Box 18, Box 17, Folder 154-209, Box 21, Box 20)
        - Foreman Observation Analysis (Box 21, Folder 210-223)
        - Reports: Foreman on the Assembly Line (Box 22, Box 21, Folder 224-234)
        - Reports: Essays (Box 22, Folder 235-240)
      - Linden, NJ
        - Background (Box 22, Folder 241-252)
        - Management and Preliminary Interviews (Box 23, Folder 253-258)
        - Worker Interviews (Box 23, Folder 259-315, Box 25, Box 24)
        - Other Interviews (Box 25, Folder 316-323, Box 26)
        - Interview Extracts (Box 26, Folder 324-348, Box 29, Box 28, Box 27)
        - Interview Analysis (Box 29, Folder 349-372)
        - Crisis Study, 1953 (Box 30, Folder 373-377)
        - Follow-up Study, 1956-1957 (Box 30, Folder 378-389, Box 31)
        - Reports (Published) (Box 31, Folder 390-396)
        - Reports (Unpublished) (Box 31, Folder 397-401)
      - Reports derived from both Linden and Framingham material (Box 32, Box 31, Folder 402-405)
      - New Departure
        - Background (Box 32, Folder 406-408)
        - Company Documents (Box 32, Folder 409-410)
        - Data (Box 32, Folder 411-414)
        - Analysis - Meetings (Box 32, Folder 415)
        - Notes (Box 32, Folder 416-417)
        - Report (Box 32, Folder 418-419)
      - Duplicates (Box 33, Folder 1-418, Box 36, Box 37, Box 34, Box 35)
  - Raytheon Study, Series IV
    This study of Raytheon Manufacturing Company was begun in 1958 with the purpose of examining the nature of work in an industry characterized by both a high level of technological development and rapid pace of on-going changes in technological work processes. The Raytheon study was conducted by the Yale Technology Project, supported in part by a grant from the National Institute of Health. At the same time, the researchers also served as consultants (Charles R. Walker and Associates) to the Raytheon Company.
    While many operations of the company were studied for research and consulting purposes, the primary focus of the study was the Mount Department in the Industrial Tube plant located in Newton, Massachusetts. The Mount Department assembled high quality vacuum tubes for use in govemnent equipment, including missiles, industrial equipment and consumer products. Interviews with management officials of Raytheon and of Industrial Tube began in the summer of 1958 and continued to be important sources of information and analysis throughout the study (section III A). A series of systematic interviews with foremen, supervisors and operators (hourly workers) was conducted in the Mount Department in 1958-1959 (III-D), a period when rising demand for tubes resulted in great pressures and stresses in the plant. These pressures were reflected in the interviews and in the observations being made of plant operations (III E, and reports, XIB), and they were analyzed in the report made to the National Institute of Health (XI C). During 1959 and 1960 many changes were made at the Industrial Tube plant, partly as a result of Walker's analysis of that "Operation Panic." In 1960 a study was made of the effects of those changes (III F, report XI D).
    Other studies of Industrial Tube followed. In 1961 an experiment was conducted in Job Enlargment (IV A), in which each operator assembled the entire tube instead of performing one segment of the assembly process in a team sequence. Another period of rising demand in 1961-1962 applied new pressures tothe plant, and this "build up" was studied to assess the effect of the changes made since Operation Panic (IV B, report file 161). In 1962 the company proposed to merge the Industrial Tube operation at Newton with the Receiving Tube operation (manufacturing a higher quantity, lower quality tube) located at Qunicy, Massachusetts. The material on this merger is somewhat vague, and a merger with another Industrial Tube plant might also have been involved. This was the final subject of the Technology Project's study of Industrial Tube.
    A variety of other studies were made at Raytheon between 1960 and 1962. Interviews with executives at the corporate level were made in 1962, with consultation about management policies (V). In 1961 an important study was made of the Receiving Tube plant in Quincy, to serve as a comparison for Industrial Tube. A special study was made of various Receiving Tube departments concerned with engineering (VI, report file 149). In 1960 and 1961 the management policies and problems of two divisions were studied, Power Tube and Semiconductor (VII-VIII, reports XI A). The studies of the corporate level, Power Tube and Semiconductor focused on management, while the Receiving Tube and Industrial Tube studies covered all aspects of production and human relations at these two electronics plants.
    - Raytheon Study Background (Box 38, Folder 1-4)
    - Raytheon Company Documents
      - Corporate Level (Box 38, Folder 5-16)
      - Industrial Tube (Box 38, Folder 17-24, Box 39)